<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A panegyricke to the most honourable and renovvned Lord, the Lord Hays vicount of Doncaster, His Maiesties of Great-Brittaine ambassadour in Germanie sung by the Rhine, interpreted by George Rodolfe Weckherlin Secr. to his High. of Wirtemberg.</title>
            <author>Weckherlin, Georg Rodolf, 1584-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25185A.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123188</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24113363</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24113363</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27199</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14883)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27199)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1844:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A panegyricke to the most honourable and renovvned Lord, the Lord Hays vicount of Doncaster, His Maiesties of Great-Brittaine ambassadour in Germanie sung by the Rhine, interpreted by George Rodolfe Weckherlin Secr. to his High. of Wirtemberg.</title>
                  <author>Weckherlin, Georg Rodolf, 1584-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By John-Wyrich Rôsslin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printet at Stutgart :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XIX [1619]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Title in ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Carlisle, James Hay, --  Earl of, 1580-1636 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27199:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27199:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PANEGYRICKE To the moſt honourable and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novvned Lord, THE LORD HAYS Vicount of Doncaſter, HIS MAIESTIES OF GREAT-BRITTAINE Ambaſſadour in Germanie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sung</hi> by THE RHINE, <hi>Interpreted</hi> by George Rodolfe Weckherlin Secr. to his High. of Wirtemberg.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:27199:2"/>
            <head>SONNET <hi>TO THE MOST NOBLE AND WORTHILY HONOURED LORD, THE LORD HAYS,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ICOVNT OF DONCASTER &amp;c.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Braue Lord in vvhom Naturs hand doth display</l>
               <l>Such daintineſſe, as ever shee can frame;</l>
               <l>VVhoſe vertuous deeds by still bright-shining Fame</l>
               <l>Engraven stand in heauens booke foray:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Doe not dislike, that my Muſe dare array</l>
               <l>Her povertie vvith your honoured name.</l>
               <l>A humble hart vvith courage to inflame</l>
               <l>Belongs to men of vvorth and noble ſvvay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The shining Sunne casting on a ſmall hill</l>
               <l>Of fertile earth her ſvveet nourishing rays,</l>
               <l>In time vvith ſeed, flovvrs and fruits doth it fill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One beame allone of your meeke grace can rayſe</l>
               <l>My lovvlie ſtyle, vvhich as yet vvanteth skill,</l>
               <l>(Though forraine) to acquire both skill and prayse.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. RODOLFE WECKHERLIN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="panegyric">
            <pb facs="tcp:27199:2"/>
            <head>A PANEGYRICKE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>MOſt noble Lord te ſee you I did long,</l>
               <l>And novv I long to ſing your vvorthie praiſe;</l>
               <l>For neuer vvorſe can bee my ſimple ſong,</l>
               <l>Then my ſilence of your renovvned bays,</l>
               <l>Whoſe luſter shall receiue (I truſt) no vvrong</l>
               <l>By thoſe ſmall flours, my humble hand doth raiſe.</l>
               <l>Nought doe I craue, nor hope I any thing,</l>
               <l>And nought but truth vvills mee your laud to ſing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My greedie eares did often gladly heare</l>
               <l>The vvorthines of your beloued Name,</l>
               <l>When Thameſis, to vvhom you are ſtill deare,</l>
               <l>When the Sea-gods and Syrens ſung the ſame,</l>
               <l>Rounding the vvorld vvith accents ſvveet and cleare,</l>
               <l>Of your perfect yet ſtill encreaſing Fame:</l>
               <l>Thus right to knovv did vvish my gotten hart</l>
               <l>If greater vvere their grace or your deſart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Novv doe I ſee, in you novv doe I find</l>
               <l>That your deſarts doe any praiſe excell;</l>
               <l>I find that Fame (els commonly too kind)</l>
               <l>Is but to you to ſcant, to hard and fell:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:27199:3"/>
               <l>Which though too great it ſeemed in my mind,</l>
               <l>Yet did my thoughts of you ſuppoſe full vvell:</l>
               <l>But novv I read, that Fame could not record,</l>
               <l>Nor I inuent, vvhat you your ſelfe afford.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let Phaebus tell if euer hee did ſee</l>
               <l>In this vaſt vvorld an other liuing vvight,</l>
               <l>VVho juſtly can vvith you compared bee,</l>
               <l>VVhom Naturs hand to frame tooke ſuch delight,</l>
               <l>Graunting to him ſuch an aſcendent Fee,</l>
               <l>VVhere els vvithall a thouſand could bee dight:</l>
               <l>In vvhom allone vvith loue ſo faire as ſvveet</l>
               <l>All gifts of mind, bodie and fortune meet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A vvorthie tvvig of a moſt auncient brood,</l>
               <l>(Of Scotlands crovvne a noble ornament)</l>
               <l>Haue you beene borne, vvhere ſome of that high blood</l>
               <l>VVere to their foes their laſt aſtonishment;</l>
               <l>Some others did vvith counſel vviſe and good</l>
               <l>The Kingdoms eaſe and their ovvne fame augment.</l>
               <l>But you to laud, 'tis needles to declare</l>
               <l>VVhat they haue beene, but onely vvhat you are.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſplendor of the ſtocke giu's but ſmall pleaſure,</l>
               <l>That often Chaunce mak's to baſe minds beſt knovvne;</l>
               <l>And ſuch a fame is but a borrovved treaſure,</l>
               <l>A lightning shevv of a vvorthleſſe renovvne:</l>
               <l>But Vertues hand, vvith her exceſſiue meaſure</l>
               <l>Spreading your laud, adorn's you vvith a crovvne,</l>
               <l>VVhich, like the Sunne, ſtill excellently bright,</l>
               <l>Doeth take of none but giu's to many light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:27199:3"/>
               <l>Not Fortunes blind franke and abuſiue hand,</l>
               <l>The vvhich to deale her vvealth confuſedly</l>
               <l>Doeth no deſarts ſee, vveigh, nor vnderſtand,</l>
               <l>But heauens Loue did courteously applie</l>
               <l>Such goods to you (your vvorth not to vvithſtand)</l>
               <l>VVhereby doe ſtill your merits multiplie.</l>
               <l>For your great hart, that no gold can recouer,</l>
               <l>Is of all gold a maſter nev'r a Louer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The chiefeſt care, richeſſe in you can breed,</l>
               <l>Is vvell to doe the chiefeſt inſtrument.</l>
               <l>Gold doth ſome men, vvhile they on gold doe feed,</l>
               <l>VVith ſtaruing paine and greedineſſe torment:</l>
               <l>But in your hart, the ground of Vertues ſeed,</l>
               <l>Yeeld's it tribut to your encouragement;</l>
               <l>And that, vvhereby ſome commonly grovve vaine,</l>
               <l>Moſt vaine to you, mak's you true glorie gaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The godlie shape, vvhich heauen did enchace</l>
               <l>VVith ſupreme skill vvithin your bodies frame,</l>
               <l>Doeth vvell appeare in your moſt vvorthie face,</l>
               <l>Like through a cloud the heauens pureſt flame:</l>
               <l>And as th'outſide of a vvell-builded place.</l>
               <l>Mak's vs beleeue, th' inſide bee vvithout blame;</l>
               <l>Thus ſeeing you my thoughts doe by mine eyes,</l>
               <l>I knovv not vvhat, more then your ſelf aduiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That monſter fierce, that all good doeth enuie,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe ſpightfull tong of no good can ſpeake vvell,</l>
               <l>May your vvhole life vvith sharpeſt look's vvell ſpie,</l>
               <l>Yet muſt it but againſt his liking tell,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:27199:4"/>
               <l>The nobleſt hart of valour, courteſie,</l>
               <l>And gallantneſſe vvithin your breaſt doe dvvell;</l>
               <l>And that your ſoule enjoyeth (moſt content)</l>
               <l>All goods that Art and Nature can preſent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhen courtlie ſport to any enterpriſe</l>
               <l>Bids you a foot or on horſebacke to fight,</l>
               <l>Or vvhen you pleaſe vvith other exerciſe</l>
               <l>That vviſeſt Kings (your Dreads) moſt vvorthieſt ſight,</l>
               <l>You may ſtill get (if ſo you vvill) the prize:</l>
               <l>But vvhen your tong vvith her ſvveet-flovving might</l>
               <l>Aſſaileth harts, then doe you plainly proue,</l>
               <l>You can ſubdue all by force or by love.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Once I vvas told (vvhen you vvent into France)</l>
               <l>Hovv vvanton Loue did faire Thetis deceiue,</l>
               <l>Hovv, vvhile your ship the Tritons made to daunce,</l>
               <l>Hee meaned her of her hart to bereaue;</l>
               <l>Hovv her greene eyes your grace and vertues glaunce</l>
               <l>Did greedily into her breaſt receiue:</l>
               <l>Your preſence braue brought her her Sonne to mind,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe image shee could no vvhere truer find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus novv my Nymfs, nay all the peoples ſtout</l>
               <l>Of Germanie, vvhich your preſence doeth grace,</l>
               <l>Ioyfully runne and ſing you round about</l>
               <l>(Glad vvith their armes and harts you to embrace)</l>
               <l>VVith minds and mouths all vvith mee crying out:</l>
               <l>Ay-during bee the happie health and grace!</l>
               <l>Still florishing may bee the praiſe and bays</l>
               <l>(As the deſarts bee great) of My lord HAYS!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:27199:4"/>
               <l>More vvould I ſay, but that your glories light,</l>
               <l>Dimming mine eyes, doth quite my mind oppreſſe:</l>
               <l>And though I ſay much, yet is it but slight,</l>
               <l>Since that much more my ſilence doth ſuppreſſe.</l>
               <l>It may bee too, that to your harts braue hight</l>
               <l>This lovvlie ſong doth cauſe but loathſomneſſe:</l>
               <l>Or (as I thinke) you are to heare more ſorie,</l>
               <l>Then prompt and glad to deſerue praiſe and glorie.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q xml:lang="lat">SPES MEA CHRISTVS IOHANN WEYRICH RÖS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SLIN</q>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Johann Weyrich Rösslin, official printer of the Württemberg court</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>Printet at Stutgart by John-Wyrich Roſslin. ANNO M.DC.XIX.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
